hey everyone welcome to another lesson
in this task automation course
today we are going to talk about and the
important concept uh in test case
generation which is called the test case
template now until now we have seen how
you can design your test cases
based on the number of combinations the
attributes
and its values right so we can
design our test cases based on what
attributes we define and then what
instances we have
and then we can create a number of
combinations
using different techniques which is
present in the test case design section
but coming back uh to the test cases
section right now we have the design but
we need to generate test cases based on
this design
so how tosca helps us do that
so coming to test case template right
it is basically a way of creating
concrete test cases out of your test
case design right so the test sheet
which we have prepared
now test case template will help us to
derive
uh those number of test cases from those
combinations
okay
now uh
this is helpful when you have similar
sequence or structure for a particular
test cases or a group of test cases
right
so
these can be modeled with a particular
template and then
test cases can be dynamically generated
using that particular test sheet which
you have already have created okay
so there are two properties uh in test
case template uh one is the schema path
which is basically the path of the data
source which contains the schema of the
template data now this data source
either could be the test design sheet
right
or you can also use the excel sheet
the other property is instance name
now when test case template are
instantiated
test case names are automatically
generated by using these instance names
of the data source which could be the
test data sheet now how to instantiate
the test case template i will show you
uh in the next video
now there are few options uh which you
should be aware of when you are creating
a test case template so there is check
template uh this is one feature
which automatically verifies your
template for any particular errors
now it is based on the schema path right
so thread data source
and uh here basically what happens is it
will compare the names which have used
in the template with the attribute names
of your test design sheet
it will also uh verify your conditions
properties test configuration parameters
so basically everything
which is used in the template
and if there are any errors it will show
you there itself while you are
performing this operation which is
called the check template okay so this
is the first thing which you should do
whenever you are creating a template you
should first verify it with the check
template okay
the next thing is uh
edit schema path now
if you have
already
linked your
data source with the test case template
you can also change it by this wizard
which is called the edit schema path
okay so you can change the schema source
there's also an option
where you can
move back to your original test case
which is called convert to test case so
once you have converted into a template
you can also go back and
make it again a test case if you want to
revert back and this is the option to do
that okay
so let's see with a real example in
tosca
to demonstrate this particular feature i
have created a new test case for our
source demo app right so we have got
this login page where we have got
username and password field and the
login button
and then we have got different user
names based on that it will show
different errors right and we have got a
password so
we want to capture the error message and
we want to login into this page right so
that's the scenario simple scenario
for that i have created this particular
test case validate login
i've got four steps open url login user
validate error message
and then there's a t-box window
operation which is basically to close
the application right so
you can actually name it as close
application
okay
now in open url uh it's just passing the
url from a configuration parameter which
is the url okay
and then login user i've got username
password error and the login button
which is i'm clicking on that
these values of the fields will be
getting it from the test data sheet okay
similarly for validate error if you
enter a invalid username or password
will get an error message and we are
going to verify it okay so the action
mode is
verify
for the error field
okay
now uh we need to have different
combinations here right of our test
cases so one will be a valid scenario
one would be an invalid scenario for
that i have created this test case
design sheet so i have got two instances
test case one and test case two
i've got the administration section
which this designer the cycle and
comments so we have all seen this
earlier right
i've got the process where i'm entering
a username and password
and as you can see i i've got different
instances of this username and password
so
i've got a standard user and a locked
out user right for two different
scenarios
and i've got the password here okay
now um coming here in verification i
have got a message verification um for
the locked out user i have got the
specific
uh message
error message which should be verified
in case of a standard user which is a
valid login i don't have any error
message right so i've left it empty
now this is the test design sheet and
this is the test case
somehow i need to link this disk is
designed
with this test case and i need to
generate two test cases out of it right
i can generate any number of test cases
but right now i have just two instances
okay so i want to generate two test
cases automatically from this test case
design sheet
with different values different test
data values right for these different
test steps
so that's that's the
feature which we are looking at and for
that we need to now convert
um this particular test case into a test
case template right because uh that's
the template which you want to use to
generate two instances out of the same
test case right
so
the steps will be same but the test data
is little different okay and depending
on how the scenario is based we want to
also specify some conditions
okay
so for that uh tosca provides you with
an option called test case template so
right click on the test case
and there you will find an option called
convert to template right so
click on that
and now this test case will be converted
into a test case template
how can you tell that you will see there
is a t symbol now associated with this
particular test case
so that t symbol will indicate that this
is a test case template and not a test
case okay
now coming to a different properties of
this discus template um we talked about
schema path right so this is where you
will link your data source which is
the test design sheet
um
and the instance name okay so you can
provide a instance name but that will
see later
now some other things are
three options which we talked about
the check template
the edit schema path
and the convert to test case right so we
can convert back to our test case
we can edit the schema path if a data
source is linked
and uh we can also check the template
for any particular errors right
so when you click on that you will see
if there are no errors it will say no
errors found in template if there are
any errors it will pop up those errors
okay
now
the most important part is to
link our test case design sheet with our
test case right
so how you can do that
where it's a very simple drag and drop
feature right
so
just drag this particular test case or
test design sheet into your test case
template
okay
once you do that
your test design sheet will be linked to
your test template
now if you want to see whether your test
case design sheet is actually linked to
your template you can just right click
on the template
and you can go to jump to schema
definition
let's do one thing let's close
this test case design section
okay
and now let's right click on
the test case template and the first
option is jump to schema definition so
when you click on that it will
automatically take you to the design
sheet which is linked to this particular
template okay
so that's the way of
verifying whether your test case design
sheet is already linked
to your test case template right
now the other thing uh which will notice
is once you link your test design sheet
with your
test case template what will happen is
the values of your test steps will
change right
so the username you can see now there is
a link provided here
which tells that this is a parameter
which is coming from the excel sheet or
the test design sheet right
so process dot username process
process.password same for here
so um
this is how it is automatically linked
with different
parameter values with this step values
okay
now although um you can see these uh the
first step is correct where we are
entering the username and password but
the second step is all about violating
the error message so we don't need to
input a username and password here right
so uh we just want to verify the error
message here so we want to get that
particular message
and in situations like this where you
want to uh specifically
put a value or link of particular value
to the test design sheet
what you can do is you can define a
parameter like excel
dot
okay dot square bracket and then it will
give you all the different attributes
here right which is present in that
particular sheet
and that's your data source which is
linked to this template okay
so here um what i want to do is i want
to
verify right so i'll say verification
dot message
okay so that will select the message and
then i will close this
so you can do this manually if it is not
automatically done when you are trying
to link the particular sheet okay for
any particular uh parameter value
so uh that completes our test case
template right
and now let's go ahead and check the
template once again so that there are no
errors found right so that we don't make
any mistakes here
so the next step is to instantiate this
template and to generate
our test cases automatically out of this
template so we'll see that in our next
video